Service accounts are incredibly powerful and
incredibly dangerous when used incorrectly.
They are like the robot users of your cloud environment.
They deploy apps, run pipelines, automate infrastructure.
Let's see how we can use it in a proper, secure manner.
In the Google Cloud console at the top, let's select the project.
So let's say my project is payment‑app‑service‑prod.
Inside the project and go inside the IAM,
and inside the IAM, you see Service Accounts.
So click on that Service Accounts.
Now here on the top you can see Create service account.
So click on Create service account.
Now give a meaningful name.
Because over a period of time you might have a couple of service
accounts and then it will be difficult to identify which service account
do what or what was the purpose of its creation.
Now click on Create and continue.
Now the console asks which role this service account should have.
This is where the things often go wrong.
People generally go and pick Basic,
and under the Basic they pick Editor because it sounds more convenient,
but we're not doing that because this is not the right way of doing.
The right way of doing is to give the least privileges roles.
For example,
let's say this service account is going to be utilized for CI/CD purpose,
and there I need only the permissions for Cloud Run,
Artifact Registry, and maybe for logs.
So there is no point in giving all the entire editor permission.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to choose a specific permission.
I'm using it for deployment,
so I'm just choosing the role as Run admin. Add
another role for Artifact Registry, Artifact Registry Reader. And similarly,
I need just one role for log, so I'm just saying that
Cloud Build Logging Service Agent, and that's it.
So I don't need to give all the permission to this specific service account.
I can give a very specific permission which is needed for
this role. And now I'm saying Done.
We should also avoid using these service account keys because
Google's security guidance is very crystal clear.
Avoid using service account keys.
Instead, use workload identity federation or
workload identity wherever possible.
The problem is service account keys are dangerous because they don't expire.
They can be copied.
They can be leaked on GitHub.
They give attackers long‑lived access, and rotating them is very painful.
So that's why whenever you're going to use the service account,
use it with the workload identity.
If at some point you want to delete this specific service account,
you can do it simply by selecting here and say Delete,
and this will delete the service account which we have created.